<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="pnrender.intro" lang="en-US"
         revision="$Revision$ $Date$"
         status="draft">
  <!-- $Id$ -->

  <chapterinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Jörg</firstname>

        <surname>Napp</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <jobtitle>Developer</jobtitle>

          <orgname>PostNuke</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Mark</firstname>

        <surname>West</surname>

        <affiliation>
          <jobtitle>Developer</jobtitle>

          <orgname>PostNuke</orgname>
        </affiliation>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <date>$Date$</date>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Smarty</keyword>

      <keyword>pnRender</keyword>

      <keyword>Xanthia</keyword>
    </keywordset>
  </chapterinfo>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section id="pnrender.intro.whatis">
    <title>What is Smarty?</title>

    <para>From the Smarty Documentation:</para>

    <blockquote>
      <attribution><ulink
      url="http://smarty.php.net/manual/en/what.is.smarty.php">The Smarty
      Documentation</ulink></attribution>

      <para>Smarty is a template engine for PHP.</para>

      <para>More specifically, it facilitates a manageable way to separate
      application logic and content from its presentation. This is best
      described in a situation where the application programmer and the
      template designer play different roles, or in most cases are not the
      same person. For example, let's say you are creating a web page that is
      displaying a newspaper article. The article headline, tagline, author
      and body are content elements, they contain no information about how
      they will be presented. They are passed into Smarty by the application,
      then the template designer edits the templates and uses a combination of
      HTML tags and template tags to format the presentation of these elements
      (HTML tables, background colors, font sizes, style sheets, etc.) One day
      the programmer needs to change the way the article content is retrieved
      (a change in application logic.) This change does not affect the
      template designer, the content will still arrive in the template exactly
      the same. Likewise, if the template designer wants to completely
      redesign the templates, this requires no changes to the application
      logic. Therefore, the programmer can make changes to the application
      logic without the need to restructure templates, and the template
      designer can make changes to templates without breaking application
      logic.</para>
    </blockquote>

    <para>Smarty makes it possible to seperate layout and code, which will
    lead to better code with less bugs.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="pnrender.intro.smartypn">
    <title>Smarty Support in PostNuke</title>

    <para>The advantages of using a template engine have convinced the
    PostNuke developers to provide access to a template engine in the core.
    Smarty has been chosen to be this template engine. The original source of
    the implementation of Smarty now found in PostNuke, called <emphasis
    role="bold">pnRender</emphasis>, was originally developed for <ulink
    url="http://www.envolution.com/">Envolution</ulink>, but has undergone a
    complete rewrite.</para>

    <para>pnRender now is a subclass of Smarty, so that developers familiar to
    Smarty can use pnRender as they would use Smarty.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="pnrender.intro.avail">
    <title>Availability</title>

    <para>pnRender is available as part of the PostNuke core in PostNuke
    .8.</para>

    <para>pnRender is available as an add-on to PostNuke .726</para>
  </section>
</chapter>